(music)
How pandemics /pænˈdemɪk 瘟疫/ spread
We live in an interconnected,
an increasingly globalized world.
Thanks to international jet travel,
people and the diseases they carry
can be in any city on the planet
in a matter of hours.
And once a virus touches down,
sometimes all it takes
is one sneeze /sniːz 打喷嚏/ to spread
the infection throughout the community.
When humans were hunter-gatherers,
roaming the wild savannas /səˈvænə 大草原/,
we were never in one place long enough,
and settlements were not large enough
to sustain /səˈsteɪn 支撑/ the transmission
of infectious /ɪnˈfɛkʃəs 传染的/ microbes /ˈmaɪkrəʊb 微生物/.
But with the advent /ˈædvent 降临/
of the agricultural revolution
10,000 years ago, and the arrival
of permanent settlements
in the Middle East, people began
living side-by-side with animals,
facilitating /fəˈsɪlɪˌteɪt 使便利/ the spread
of bacteria and viruses
between cattle /ˈkætəl 牛 家畜 / and humans.
Epidemics /ˌɛpɪˈdɛmɪk  流行病/ and pandemics /pænˈdemɪk 瘟疫/ come
in many shapes and forms.
In 2010, for instance,
a devastating /ˈdɛvəˌsteɪt 摧毁/ earthquake struck Haiti /ˈheɪtɪ/,
forcing thousands of people
into temporary refugee camps.
Within weeks, the camps had become
breeding grounds for cholera /ˈkɒlərə 霍乱/,
a bacteria spread by contaminated /kən'tæmineit 污染/ water,
triggering a country-wide epidemic /ˌɛpɪˈdɛmɪk  流行病/.
But the most common cause
of epidemics are viruses,
such as measles /ˈmiːzəlz 麻疹/, influenza /ˌɪnflʊˈenzə 流感/ and HIV.
And when they go global,
we call them pandemics.
Pandemics have occurred
throughout human history,
Some have left scars on the tissue
and bone of their victims,
while evidence for others
comes from preserved /prɪˈzɜ:vd 保存/ DNA.
For instance, scientists
have recovered DNA
from the bacteria
that transmits tuberculosis /tjʊˌbɜːkjʊˈləʊsɪs  肺结核/
from the remains of ancient
Egyptian mummies /ˈmʌmɪ 木乃伊/.
And in 2011,
scientists investigating a plague /pleɪɡ 瘟疫/
pit /pɪt 坑/ in the city of London
were able to reconstruct
the genome /dʒi:nəum 基因组/ of Yersinia pestis /鼠疫/,
the bacterium /bækˈtɪərɪəm 细菌/ responsible for the Black
Death of the 14th century.
It is thought the plague /pleɪɡ 瘟疫/
originated /əˈrɪdʒɪˌneɪt 起源于/ in China
in around 1340,
spreading west along the Silk Road,
the caravan /ˈkærəˌvæn 旅行队/ route running
from Mongolia /mɒŋˈɡəʊlɪə/ to the Crimea /kraɪˈmɪə 克里米亚/.
In 1347, the plague reached
the Mediterranean /ˌmɛdɪtəˈreɪnɪən/,
and by 1400, it had killed in excess /ˈɛksɛs 过量/ of
34 million Europeans,
earning it the title,
the Great Mortality /mɔːˈtælɪtɪ 必死性/.
It was later historians /hɪˈstɔːrɪən 历史学家/
who called it the Black Death.
However, by far the greatest
pandemic killer
is influenza /ˌɪnflʊˈenzə 流感/.
Flu is constantly circulating
between the Southern and Northern Hemispheres /ˈhɛmɪˌsfɪə 半球/.
In North America and Europe,
seasonal flus occur
every autumn and winter.
As the majority of children and adults will have
been exposed to the virus in previous seasons,
these illnesses are usually mild /maɪld/.
However, every 20 to 40 years or so
the virus undergoes a dramatic /drəˈmætɪk / mutation /mjuːˈteɪʃən 变异/.
Usually this occurs when a wild flu virus
circulating in ducks and farm poultry /ˈpəʊltrɪ 家禽/
meets a pig virus,
and they exchange genes /dʒiːn/.
This process is known as antigenic /ˌæntɪˈdʒenɪk 抗原的/ shift
and has occurred throughout human history.
The first recorded
pandemic occurred in 1580.
The 18th and 19th centuries
saw at least six further pandemics.
In terms of mortality,
none can compare with the Great
Flu Pandemic of 1918.
The first indication of the pandemic
came in the spring, when American
troops in northern France
began complaining of chills /tʃɪl 寒冷/,
headaches and fever /ˈfiːvə 发热/.
Then, the following September, at a U.S.
Army barracks /ˈbærək 兵营/ near Boston /ˈbɒstən/,
soldiers started collapsing /kəˈlæps 倒塌/ on parade /pəˈreɪd 游行/,
prompting /prɒmpt 提示/ their removal
to the camp infirmary /ɪnˈfɜːmərɪ 医务室/.
As a surgeon there recalled,
two hours after admission, they had
the mahogany /məˈhɒɡənɪ 红褐色/ spots over the cheekbones /ˈtʃiːkˌbəʊn  颧骨/
and a few hours later
you can begin to see the cyanosis /saiəˈnəusis 黄萎病/
extending from their ears
and spreading all over the face.
It is only a matter of a few hours
then until death comes,
and it is simply a struggle
for air until they suffocate /ˈsʌfəˌkeɪt 窒息/.
On the S.S. Leviathan,
a huge American transport
en /en 过程/ route to Bordeaux /bɔːˈdəʊ 波尔多/,
sick men hemorrhaged /ˈhemərɪdʒ 出血/
blood from their noses,
turning the decks between their bunks /bʌŋk 铺位/
slick /slɪk 光滑/ with bodily /人体的/ fluids /ˈfluːɪd 液体/.
Meanwhile, British soldiers returning
from northern France on furlough /ˈfɜːləʊ 休假 暂时解雇/
introduced the flu to Dover /ˈdəʊvə/
and other Channel ports,
from where the virus
was carried by rail to London.
By the time the pandemic
had run its course
in April 1919,
an estimated 675,000 Americans
and 230,000 Britons were dead.
In India alone, some 10
million were killed,
and worldwide the death toll
was an astonishing /əˈstɒnɪʃɪŋ 惊人的/ 50 million.
But that was then.
Today, planes can transport viruses
to any country on the globe
in a fraction /ˈfrækʃən 小部分/ of the time it took in 1918.
In February 2003, for instance,
a Chinese doctor arrived
at the Metropole Hotel in Hong Kong
feeling unwell.
Unknown to him, he was harboring /hɑ:bəriŋ 怀有/ a new
animal-origin virus called SARS,
short for Severe /sɪˈvɪə 严重的/ Acute /əˈkjuːt 急剧的/
Respiratory /rəˈspɪrətrəri 呼吸的/ Syndrome /ˈsɪndrəʊm 综合征/.
Within 24 hours of checking into Room 913,
sixteen other guests had been infected,
and over the following days five boarded
planes to overseas destinations,
spreading the virus to Vietnam,
Singapore and Canada.
Flights between Hong Kong, Toronto /təˈrɒntəʊ/ and other
international cities were quickly grounded
and thanks to other emergency measures,
a pandemic was averted /əˈvɜːt 避免/.
By the time the outbreak
was over four months later,
SARS had infected 29 countries worldwide
and more than 1,000 people were dead.
For all that the virus
was rapidly contained, however,
there was little that could be done
about the alarming news reports
carried by cable news
channels and the Internet.
As bloggers added to the hysteria /hɪˈstɪərɪə 歇斯底里/
by spreading unfounded
conspiracy /kənˈspɪrəsɪ 阴谋/ theories,
tourism in Hong Kong and other
affected cities ground to a halt /hɔːlt/,
costing businesses more
than 10 billion U.S. dollars.
One business, however, did very well.
Above all, SARS was a reminder that pandemics
have always been associated with panic /ˈpænɪk 惊恐/.
If history teaches us anything,
it's that while pandemics may start small,
their impacts can be as dramatic
as wars and natural disasters.
The difference today
is that science gives us
the ability to detect pandemics
right at the very beginning
and to take action
to mitigate /ˈmɪtɪˌɡeɪt 减轻/ their impacts
before they spread too widely.
(music)